Guide to the John Harding papers, 1927-2004.
Harding, John papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
John Harding papers, 1927-2004.
23-13-3872
John Harding
6 cubic feet.
Manuscripts, Printed Materials, Publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, publications, photographs, and subject files relating to John Harding's career and his work in social psychology.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Human Development and Family Studies, Cornell University.
John Harding received his B.A. from the University of Minnesota and his M.A. and Ph.D. in psychology from Harvard in 1943. In 1942 he held a Rockefeller Foundation Fellowship at the Princeton University Office of Public Opinion Research. During W.W.II he served as a research psychologist with the U.S. Army Air Forces. From 1946-1952 he carried out research on methods combatting prejudice and discrimination for the Commission on Community Interrelations of the American Jewish Congress, which was founded by Kurt Lewin and from 1952-1953 he was employed on a test development project at New York University's Research Center for Human Relations. In 1953 Harding came to Cornell University in the Dept. of Child Development and Family Relationships and was associated with the Cornell Program in Social Psychiatry. His research was in the areas of intergroup relations and mental health. He was a member of the American Psychological Association, the Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, and the Society for Research in Child Development. Harding retired from Cornell in 1989.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, publications, photographs, and subject files relating to John Harding's career and his work in social psychology.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Harding, John; Harding, John; Lewin, Kurt, 1890-1947.; Cornell University--Faculty.; New York State College of Human Ecology.Dept. of Human Development and Family Studies; Cornell Program in Social Psychiatry.; American Jewish Congress.; Psychology--Study and teaching.; Stereotypes--(Social psychology)
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Research and Professional
Series IV. Course Material
Series V. Programs and Initiatives
Series VI. Department, College, and University Committees and Material
Series VII. Publications
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical
  - Biographical Information, 1966-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personnel File, 1951-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Government Security Clearance Information, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Friends, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Friends, 1977-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bronfenbrenner, Urie, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gatch, Gerald - Correspondence, Publications, 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Goodchilds, Jackie - Correspondence, Papers, 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Loevinger, Jane - Research, 1973-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Rose, Arnold, 1947-1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Schuman, Howard, 1961-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Wakim, Suad, 1959-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Journal of Social Issues - McCord Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues (SPSSI) - Katz Supplement, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Katz Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues (SPSSI) and Journal of Social Issues - Correspondence, 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Journal of Social Issues-SPSSI Council, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Journal of Social Issues - Brewster Smith, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Journal of Social Issues - Robert Chin, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letter from Harding to Dr. Launor Carter, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Series III. Research and Professional
  - Personality Tests, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Calibration Study - Stirlin and Midtown, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Psychologists, 1989; 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Washington University Sentence Completion Test, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Code to Moral Dilemma Questionnaire (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Moral Dilemma Interviews (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Prejudice Project, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Prejudice Project - Budget, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Prejudice Project - Questionnaire, Appendix, Summary Data, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Reviews of Articles - Child Development Journal; Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 1964-1971; 1975 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Midterm Study, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Rosen Report - Women's Role in Academic Achievement, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Friedrich Research - Women's Role in Academic Achievement, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Project Literacy - Princeton Conference, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Reading Research Materials, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Initial Teaching Alphabet (I.T.A.) Project, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Gray Oral Reading Tests, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Social Problems Test - Friedrich (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Cornell - Lund Report, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Department of Behavioral Sciences - Harvard School of Public Health, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Harvard Social Psychiatry Program - General, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Health Opinion Survey, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - North Carolina Research in Social Psychiatry (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Social Psychiatry, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Social Psychiatry, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Changing Intergroup Attitudes - Kutner, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Handbook of Social Psychology, 1963-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Handbook of Social Psychology - Article, 1952-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Articles on Black Americans and Racial Prejudice, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Stereotypes" - by John Harding (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Measurement of Prejudice - Harvard, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Worksheets on Morale- Harvard - Psychology Department, no date (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - APA Symposium - Paper - "The Conceptualization and Measurement of Prejudice", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Generalizations, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General Factor Questionnaire, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Prejudice - Resources, Articles, 1958-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Measurement of Prejudice - Research and Articles, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - APA Paper - "How Old is Scientific Psychology?", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - American Psychologist Article - "The Crisis in German Psychology: 1796-1806", 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Lecture Notes on German Sociology and Psychology, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - German Psychologists, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Seminar on Hermeneutics and Scriptural Interpretation, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - AARP Tompkins County Chapter, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Aging Field Studies, 1962-1992 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Allport, Gordon, 1962-1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Aging Proposal - "Developing Home Support Services for Rural Elderly, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Aging Proposal, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Concentrated Care Proposal, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Diagnosis Related Group (DRG) Mini-Conference, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Project Reports - Concerning Long Term Care, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Learning Instruction and Learning Disabilities, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Lecture by Jules Sugarman, 1970;1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Compensatory Preschool Planning, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Influence Techniques, 1952-1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Parental Discipline Techniques, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Observational Methods Conference, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Observation Records in the Nursery School, 1954; 1960s (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Observation Records of Betty, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Biemiller Observation Records (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Montessori School - Ithaca, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Research in Human Ecology, 1971-1985 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - An Experiment in Training Volunteer Trainers, 1948-1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Social Psychology, 1949-1968 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Work on Oriented Family Support System, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Project Proposals, 1952-1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Behavioristic and Humanistic Approaches, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Explanations in Psychology, 1976-1995 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Prejudice Monograph, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Reactions Article and Questionnaire, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Social Problems Questionnaire; Battery of Tests for Measuring Prejudice, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Prejudice Battery, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Chein, I. - ATDP Scales, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Morse, North Carolina - Antisemitism (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - New York University Attitude Measurement, 1959-1976 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Prejudice Research by Others, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Psychology Honors Thesis - Schoener, Gary, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Watson-Glaser Critical Thinking Appraisal Scales, 1927; 1952 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Project Proposals in Child Development and Family Relations, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Proposals - For a Human Ecology Quarterly, Seminar for Graduate Students, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Alphabetical Order
    - Archives - Cornell (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Gordon Allport - Symposium, 1969-1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Affirmative Action, 1982-1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - American Psychological Association Symposium, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - American Psychological Association Papers, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
    - American Psychological Association - Assembly for Scientific and Applied Psycholgoy, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 7A)
    - American Psychological Association Debate, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Behavior Trends, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Bringham - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Commission on Community Interrelations of the American Jewish Congress Material, 1940s (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Commission on Community Interrelations of the American Jewish Congress Bibliography, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Cherry Article and Correspondence, 1998-2002 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Coping with Emergencies by the Rural Elderly, 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Cornell Crisis, 1969-1999 (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
    - Doktorov - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - East Hill School, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Elderplan, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 1963-1967 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Faculty Anti-War Group, 1971-1994 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Gerald Gratch, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Heidegger, 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - History and Philosophy of Science and Technology Program at Cornell, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - History of Psychology, 1978-1985 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Holt, Bob, 1950-1992 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Institute for Single Parent Family, Inc., 1986 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Meehl-Correspondence, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Modeling Medicaid (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Quality Circles, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Race Relations, 1968-1992 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Schuyler County, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Pepinsky Research, 1959-1991 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Psychoanalysis, 1986-1998 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Selltiz, Claire, 1948-1999 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Sibulkin, Amy, 1981-1987 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Social Psychology - History of Psychology at Cornell, 1940s (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Stern Symposium, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Story Reading Project, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Students, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Study of Lives, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - University Faculty - Cornell, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - University Senate, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Wethington Materials, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Whyte, Bill, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Springdale Project
    - Springdale - Correspondence, Reports, 1955-1961 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Activities Interviews, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Cornell Community Survey - Schedule C, no date (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Coordinating Interviews, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Staff Materials, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Dohrenuend Analysis, 1950s (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Field Reports, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Social Creativity Projects, 1950s (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Appendix A: Detailed Item Information, no date (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Series IV. Course Material
  - Human Development and Family Studies (HEFS) Course 334B, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - HDFS 218 - Adulthood and Aging - Literature Searching, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - HDFS 665 - Moral Development and Ego Development, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - HDFS 665 - Moral Development and Ego Development, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - HDFS 111 and 115 - Conception Through the Middle Childhood Years, 1959-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - HDFS 360, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - HDFS 218, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Child Development and Family Relations 210 - Child Guidance, 1956-1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - HDFS 380, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Child Development and Family Relations 502, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Child Development and Family Relations 502, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - HDFS 401, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - HDFS 401 - Papers, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Child Development and Family Relations 210, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Child Development and Family Relations 317/318, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - HDFS Course 365, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - HDFS Course 365 - Handouts, 1979-1986 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - HDFS Course 365, 1983-1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Reading Lists for Graduate Students in Social and Personality Development, 1969; 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Lecture on Aging (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Course - "Innovations in Graduate Education", 1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Kendal-Skinner Seminar, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lyceum at Kendal (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Series V. Programs and Initiatives
  - Family Art Program - "Effects upon Individual Creativity and Family Interaction of Participation in a Creative Expression Program", 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Art Program Report, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Cornell Story Reading Project - Reports, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sample Story Reading Session, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Cornell Story Reading Project - Reports, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Cornell Story Reading Project - Final Report, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Project Head Start, 1957-1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Head Start Project, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Head Start Research, 1966-1973 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Project Head Start - Research Proposal, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Parent Interview Schedule - Head Start, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Parent Interview Schedule - Samples, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Achievement Test Results in Ithaca School System, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Elementary Teaching Certification (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Henry St. John Project, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Henry St. John School, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Henry St. John Report (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Report and Tabulations - Bernstein, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Program Descriptions, Henry St. John and others - Connie Smith (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Preschool Inventory (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Series VI. Department, College, and University Committees and Material
  - Human Development and Family Studies (HDFS) Planning Steering Committee, 1973-1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Human Development and Family Studies (HDFS) Memos, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Child Development and Family Relations/Human Development and Family Studies Historical Sketch, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - HDFS Faculty Meetings, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - HDFS Faculty Meetings, 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Human Ecology Faculty Meetings, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Human Ecology Faculty Meetings, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Human Ecology Faculty Meetings, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Colloquium Presentations and Comments by Harding, 1967-1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Colloquium Presentations and Comments by Harding, 1980-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Female Studies, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - HDFS Departmental Council, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - HDFS Conference on Research Perspectives in the Ecology of Human Development, August 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - HDFS Seminar - 18th Century Psychology, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 2A)
  - Human Ecology Anniversary Symposium, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - College Study Committee, 1962-1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - College of Human Ecology Long Term Planning, 1968-1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - New York State Report on School Integration, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Perkins Letter and Sproull Memorandum, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Prediction Study - Donald Turner, 1940-1979 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Donald Turner (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - HDFS Chair Search, 1977, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - HDFS Chair Search, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series VII. Publications
  - Prejudice and the Norm of Rationality - Article, 1963-1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - New York University Research - Publications, 1952-1960 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Additional Publications, 1938-1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Adolescence, 1969-1986 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Allport's - The Nature of Prejudice - Revisions, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - PhD Thesis, The Measurement of Civilian Morale, Harding, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Publications by Harding, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Publication by Harding-"How to Conduct a Community Self-Survey of Civil Rights" - Analysis Plans- Commission of Community Interrelations of the American Jewish Congress (Box 4, Folder 20A)
  - Publications by Harding, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Publications by Harding, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Publications by Harding, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Publications - Media Services Contributions, 1979-1987 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Humanism and Behaviorism: Dialogue and Growth, Ed. Wandersman, A.; Problems in Social Psychology: An Interdisciplinary Approach, Ed. Hulett, J.E., 1976; 1952 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Articles by Margaret Harding, 1949-1970 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Autobiography by Jacob Harding, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Dedication of Stephen Wise Congress House - published by American Jewish Congress, April 1951 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Dissertation by Donald Campbell "The Generality of a Social Attitude", 1947 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation by J. D. Goodchilds "Effects of Being Witty on Position in the Social Structure of a Small Group, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dissertation by Jane LaFargue "A Study to Determine Perceived Racial Prejudice and Follow-Up Preventive Child Health Care Among Low-Income Black Families", 1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Office of Institutional Studies "Analysis of Citizenship Recess", Fall 1970 (Box 6, Folder 10)